DANIELA MASSICETI

1 Denison Street Sydney, NSW 2060, Australia Senior Researcher (Machine Learning)
Microsoft Research, Sydney

daniela.massiceti@gmail.com https://danielamassiceti.github.io

SUMMARY

I am a multi-disciplinary machine learning (ML) researcher working on "teachable AI" - sytems that can learn on-the-fly from small amounts of noisy, real-world data provided by an end-user. I hold a Ph.D in computer vision, a M.Sc in Neuroscience, and a B.Sc in Electrical & Computer Engineering. My core interests lie in developing ML models that drive interactive, teachable experiences across a range of domains - from accessibility to mixed reality. Some examples include i) my current work on teachable object recognisers for people who are blind, ii) my PhD work on chat bots that can answer questions about an image, and iii) my MSc work on navigation in virtual reality environments using spatial sound. My full research portfolio can be found here. I value working with a multi-disciplinary team, and am dedicated to doing research with real-world impact.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Researcher. Microsoft Research, Sydney

Aug 2022-present

- Continuing remotely with the Teachable AI Experiences (TaiX) team. Manager: Dr Cecily Morrison MBE

Senior Researcher. Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Apr 2021-Jul 2022

- Member of Teachable AI Experiences (TaiX) team. Manager: Dr Cecily Morrison MBE
- Machine learning lead in the winning team of the global internal Microsoft Hackathon
- Recipient of the Innovating for the Future Award at the Microsoft Ability Summit

Researcher. Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Feb 2020-Mar 2021

- Member of Project Tokyo team. Manager: Dr Cecily Morrison MBE
- Collected the ORBIT dataset and open-sourced the ORBIT Teachable Object Recognition benchmark

Postdoctoral Research Fellow. St Edmund's College, University of Cambridge

Apr 2020-Sep 2022

- Non-stipendiary research fellowship

EDUCATION & SELECTED AWARDS

D.Phil Engineering - Machine Learning (awarded with no corrections), University of Oxford

2015-2019

- Thesis: "Computer Vision & Natural Language Processing for People with Vision Impairment"
- Supervisors: Prof. Philip H.S. Torr, Dr Stephen Hicks. Examiners: Prof. Andrew Zisserman, Prof. Kristen Grauman.
- Bronze Engineering Award at *STEM4Britain* (awarded by UK Parliament House of Commons) (2018)
- Winner of University of Oxford Tri-Innovate Competition (start-up pitch competition) (2017)

M.Sc Neuroscience (with distinction), University of Oxford

2014-2015

- Research project w Prof. Rafal Bogacz "Modelling Parkinson's Disease tremor with networks of weakly-coupled oscillators"
- Research project w Dr Stephen Hicks "Sonic Vision: 3D visual-to-audio mappings for non-sighted navigation"

B.Sc Engineering - Electrical & Computer (cum laude), University of Cape Town

2010-2014

- With Prof. Fred Nicolls "Occluded body pose estimation and reconstruction of bed-bound patients for hospital monitoring"
- Best final year thesis (Siemens Prize) and finalist in SAIEE National Student Project Competition (2013)
- Top final year B.Sc Engineering gradudate (Engineering Council of South Africa medal; 2013)
- Top 4^{th} , 3^{rd} & 2^{nd} -year student in Engineering faculty (2013, 2012, 2011)
- Top 4^{th} , 3^{rd} & 2^{nd} -year student in B.Sc Electrical & Computer Engineering (2013, 2012, 2011)
- UCT Engineering Faculty Dean's Merit List ($\geq 75\%$ average) (2010–2013)
- Golden Key International Honours Society (top academic 15% at UCT) (2010–2013)

National Senior Certificate (IEB South Africa), Holy Rosary School, Johannesburg

1996 - 2009

- Within top 50 Year 12 students nationally (top 5% in ≥ 6 IEB subjects across South Africa) (2009)
- Deputy Head Girl, Dux Scholar, School Honours (all-round academic, sporting and cultural excellence) (2009)

INTERNSHIP/CONSULTANCY POSITIONS

Machine Learning Intern, Microsoft Research, Cambridge

June-Dec~2019

- Developed machine learning models which learn to recognise objects after only seeing a few examples (few-shot recognition)
- Contact: Dr Cecily Morrison MBE cecilym@microsoft.com

Machine Learning Intern, OxSight Ltd

Nov 2018

- Developed a machine learning model for predicting which images regions are salient for OxSight's smart-spectacles
- Contact: Dr Stephen Hicks stephen.hicks@oxsight.co.uk

Machine Learning Consultant, London Vision Clinic

May-July 2018

- Consulted on machine learning methods for automatic keratoconus prediction from retinal scans
- Contact: Dr Dan Reinstein dzr@londonvisionclinic.com

Visiting Student, Computer Vision Lab Dresden (CVLD), Technische Universität Dresden

Apr 2015

- Compared methods for image-based camera relocalisation using random forests and neural networks
- The project resulted in a paper which was accepted and published in ICRA 2017
- Contact: Prof Carsten Rother carsten.rother@iwr.uni-heidelberg.de

RESEARCH

Selected Publications. See Google Scholar for full list

- 1. Wang J., Lukasiewicz, T., Massiceti, D., Hu, X., Pavlovic, V., Neophytou, A., 2022. NP-Match: When Neural Processes meet Semi-Supervised Learning. In 2022 International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML).
- Bronskill, J.*, Massiceti, D.*, Patacchiola, M.*, Hofmann, K., Nowozin, S., Turner, R.E., 2021. Memory Efficient Meta-Learning with Large Images. In 2021 Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS).
- 3. Massiceti, D., Zintgraf, L., Bronskill, J., Theodorou, L., Harris, M.T., Cutrell, E., Morrison, C., Hofmann, K. and Stumpf, S., 2021. *ORBIT: A Real-World Few-Shot Dataset for Teachable Object Recognition*. In 2021 IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV).
- 4. Theodorou, L., Massiceti, D., Zintgraf, L., Stumpf, S., Morrison, C., Cutrell, E., Harris, M. T. and Hofmann, K, 2021. Disability-first Dataset Creation: Lessons from Constructing a Dataset for Teachable Object Recognition with Blind and Low Vision Data Collectors. In 2021 ACM Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS).
- Grayson, M., Thieme, A., Marques, R., Massiceti, D., Cutrell, E., Morrison, C., 2020. A Dynamic AI System for Extending the Capabilities of Blind People. In Extended Abstracts of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA).
- 6. Massiceti, D.*, Dokania, P.K.*, Siddharth, N.* and Torr, P.H.S., 2018. Visual Dialogue without Vision or Dialogue. In 2018 Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) [Critiquing & Correcting Trends in ML Workshop].
- Massiceti, D., Siddharth, N., Dokania, P.K. and Torr, P.H.S., 2018. FlipDial: A Generative Model for Two-Way Visual Dialogue. In IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR). [accepted as oral]
- 8. Massiceti, D., Hicks, S.L. and van Rheede, J.J., 2018. Stereosonic Vision: exploring visual-to-auditory sensory substitution mappings in an immersive virtual reality navigation paradigm. PLOS ONE 13(7): e0199389.
- Hou, Q*, Massiceti, D.*, Dokania, P.K., Wei, Y., Cheng, M.M. and Torr, P.H.S., 2017. Bottom-up top-down cues for weakly-supervised semantic segmentation. In 2017 International Conference on Energy Minimization Methods in Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (EMMCVPR).
- 10. Massiceti, D., Krull, A., Brachmann, E., Rother, C. and Torr, P.H.S., 2017. *Random forests versus Neural Networks What's best for camera localization?*. In 2017 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA).

Patents

- On an innovation in few-shot learning applied to a metaverse application [under submission, commercially sensitive]

Selected Presentations

Panel Discussion, Pursuing a Resilient and Sustainable Global Society - Microsoft Research 30th Anniversary Panel Series
on Generations of Inspirational and Impactful Research

Dec 2021

 Sponsor Talk, Advancing Real-world Few-shot Learning with the ORBIT Dataset - WiML workshop, NeurIP Invited Talk, Using Few-shot Learning to Realize Teachable AI Systems - Microsoft Research Summit Invited Talk, A Real-World Few-Shot Dataset for Teachable Object Recognition - VizWiz workshop, CVPR Guest Lecture, An Introduction to Dataset Bias - Department of Computer Science, University of Cambridg Student Talk, A Generative Model for Visual Dialogue - OxBridge Women in Computer Science Conference 	Oct 2021 Jun 2021 ge Feb 2020
- Invited Talk, Teaching Computers to Chat - ATOM Science Society	Aug 2017
SELECTED SCHOLARSHIPS & GRANTS	
 Facebook AI Research ParlAI Grant Skye Foundation Scholarship, and University of Oxford Engineering Science Departmental Scholarship Clarendon Fund Scholarship University of Cape Town Engineering Faculty Scholarship 	2018-2019 2017-2019 2015-2019 2014-2015 2011-2013 2012-2013 2010
LEADERSHIP	
Organising committee member of the <i>VizWiz workshop</i> - VizWiz is an annual workshop at CVPR on computer vision research/technologies for the blind/low-vision computer vision computed the ORBIT Few-Shot Object Recognition Challenge in 2022, a new ML competition at the workshop.	v
Organising committee member of the <i>Deep Learning Indaba</i> — The Indaba is a globally-recognised community for African inclusion in machine learning and artificial intelligue. — I co-organised the Indaba machine learning summer school in 2018 & 2019 — I co-founded & lead the Mentorship Programme in 2020 & 2021, facilitating 200+ mentorship sessions for Africa	-
Industry officer of University of Oxford Women in Computer Science — I engaged with society's industry partners (including Google, DeepMind, Facebook, Bloomberg, Microsoft, and — I coordinated termly office visits, technical talks, and coding and interview preparation workshops	2018-2019 nd others)
Committee member of University of Oxford Women in Engineering — I coordinated the 1 st Women in Engineering Research Symposium in May 2018	2016-2019
President of Middle Common Room (MCR), Pembroke College — I was elected to represent the Pembroke College graduate body (350 members) in the College's Governing Body — I introduced per-student subsidies for welfare support, extra-curricular and academic activity	2017 Committee
Treasurer and vice president of Middle Common Room (MCR), Pembroke College — I managed an annual cash flow of £40,000-£50,000, and acquired £4000+ funding for academic and cultural end of Pembroke College Finance & Planning Committee and Student Development Committee	2015-2017 events
EXTRA-CURRICULAR	
 Entrepreneurship I began a web-design company for business/personal website development I won a start-up competition at University of Oxford with an assistive tool idea for visually-impaired people Outreach 	013—present 2017
- I mentored 1 student in the Oxford Engineering, Science and Technology (OxFEST) Mentorship Scheme	2018-2019 2016-2018 2009-2013 sics 2013
REFERENCES ON REQUEST	